Guide to the English Nationality Room Committee Collection, 1931-1981 UA.40.07
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Volume III: Dedication 1952, Gifts 1948-1963, Clippings 1930-1961, III.
  - Clippings, 1930-1961; 3.
    - Greeting card with picture of the Churchill Arch (Item 19)
    - Pttsburgh Sun-Telegraph article, "Nationality Room at Pitt Duplicate of Parliament", November 16, 1952 (Item 20)
    - Pitt News article, "Queen Mother Writes Pitt on English Room", November 21, 1951 (Item 21)
    - Pittsburgh Press article, "A Touch of Old England", November 16, 1952 (Item 22)
    - Christian Science Monitor article, "Dramatizing a Period: University of Pittsburgh Dedicates Its Eighteenth 'Nationality' Classroom", November 22, 1952 (Item 23)
    - Pitt News article, "Ceremony Tonight New English Room Dedication", November 21, 1952 (Item 24)
    - Pittsburgh Press article, "Ascent of Elizabeth II Quickens Hope of Britons", February 17, 1952 (Item 25)
    - Pttsburgh Sun-Telegraph article, "British Donor of Pitt Gifts A Real 'Jigsaw Puzzler'", November 21, 1952 (Item 26)
    - Pttsburgh Post-Gazette article, "Pitt Will Dedicate English Room Friday", November 17, 1952 (Item 27)
    - Pitt News article, "All Nationality Classrooms, a Twenty-five Year Project, Soon Expected to be Finished", July 30, 1952 (Item 28)
    - Pittsburgh Press article, "English Room at Pitt Dedicated with Pageantry", November 16, 1952 (Item 29)
    - Pttsburgh Sun-Telegraph article, "Englishmen's Wives Say City Impressive", November 22, 1952 (Item 30)
    - Pttsburgh Sun-Telegraph article, "There'll Always be a Bit of England Here at Pitt", November 20, 1952 (Item 31)
    - Pttsburgh Post-Gazette article and photos, "British Envoy to Attend Pitt Ceremony", November 20, 1952 (Item 32)
    - Pitt News article, "Member of Parliament Speaks at English Room Dedication", November 19, 1952 (Item 33)
    - Pttsburgh Post-Gazette article, "British M.P. to Open Pitt's English Room", November 11, 1952 (Item 34)
    - Evening Star article, "Englishman is Speaker at College", November 22, 1952 (Item 35)
    - Beaver Valley Times article, "Beaver Firm Helps Complete 'English Room'", November 17, 1952 (Item 36)
    - The Connoisseur article, "University of Pittsburgh", March 1953 (Item 37)
    - Children's Newspaper article, "Classrooms of the Nations", March 31, 1953 (Item 38)
    - Border Telegraph article, "Fostering Goodwill", March 31, 1953 (Item 39)
    - Weekly Scotsman article, "Palace - Only One Royal Standard", July 7, 1953 (Item 40)
    - Pitt News article, "Oxford Professor Stops at Pitt to Promote Study in England", November 13, 1953 (Item 41)
    - Invitations to celebrate the 366th Anniversary of the Defeat of the Spanish Armada, July 1954 (Item 42)
    - Pttsburgh Post-Gazette article, "They Like Nip in Pittsburgh's Air", May 17, 1955 (Item 43)
    - Pitt News article, "A Royal Setting", October 5, 1955 (Item 44)
    - Pitt News article, "Blood, Sweat, and Tears", March 4, 1957 (Item 45)
    - New York Times Magazine article, "Behind Britain's Foreign Policy", June 17, 1956 (Item 46)
    - Pittsburgh Press article, "17th Century English 'Curled'", May 8, 1961 (Item 47)
    - Postcard of Herald's College, Earl Marchal's Throne (Item 48)
    - Postcard of Herald's College, Earl Marshal's Court (Item 49)
    - Postcard of Herald's College, Chimneypiece in the Public Office, by William Emmot, 1675 (Item 50)
    - Postcard of Herald's College, South Front (Item 51)
    - Postcard of Heraldic Shields (Item 52)
    - Postcard of the Herald of Charles I (Item 53)
    - Postcard of Herald Proclaiming the Peace of Versailles (1783), Recognizing American Independance (Item 54)
    - Booklet on the proposed Franklin Delano Roosevelt Memorial (Item 55)
- Volume IV: Architectural Design 1929-1956, Window Rondelles 1952-1958, Furniture 1954-1959, IV.
  This volume contains correspondence and specifications for the various proposed architectural designs for the English Nationality Room, including an Elizabethan Oak Room, Queen Anne design, Tudor design, and the house of Commons design which came to fruition. Other correspondence is concerned with features that were added to the room after it was dedicated, including furniture and the window rondelles, which feature the coats of arms for several English universities.
  - Overview of Design Proposals, 1956; 1.
  - John Rothenstein, 1929; 2.
    - Letter from Rothenstein to Ruth Crawford Mitchell, April 11, 1929 (Volume 4, Item 1)
    - Specificaton for Jacobean Room and Queen Anne Room, April 25, 1929 (Item 2)
  - Charles Roberson of London, 1931-1934; 3.
    - Letter from Charles Roberson to Mitchell, June 11, 1931 (Item 1)
    - List of woodwork and carving by Roberson (Item 2)
    - Letter from Nigel Stuart to Mitchell, March 5, 1934 (Item 3)
    - Description of Elizabethan Oak Room from Exeter College (Item 4)
    - Photo of Elizabethan Oak Room from Exeter College (Item 5)
    - Preliminary Memorandum, November 1934 (Item 6)
  - A.E. Richardson, 1936; 4.
    - Comments on Preliminary Designs Submitted for the English Memorial Classroom in the Cathedral of Learning by A.E. Richardson, July 1936 (Item 1)
    - Floor Plan of the Christopher Wren design (Item 2)
    - Wall Sections of the Christopher Wren design (Item 3)
    - Sketched View of the Christopher Wren design (Item 4-5)
  - Walter Godfrey, 1936-1946; 5.
    - Correspondence, 1936 (Item 1)
      - Description of the Proposed English Room by Walter H. Godfrey, 1936; 1.
      - Description of Walter Godfrey's Career, 1956; 2.
      - Extract of a letter Dr. Bowman from W.G. Constable, July 23, 1936; 3.
      - Mitchell to Dr. Mansbridge, August 18, 1936; 4.
      - Revisions of Preliminary Elevations for the English Room, September 1, 1936; 5.
    - Correspondence, 1937 (Item 2)
      - Summary of Mitchell's conferences in London, March 9, 1937; 1.
      - Mary Gillick to Mitchell, January 22, 1937; 2.
      - Mitchell to Godfrey, August 4, 1937; 3.
      - Godfrey to Mitchell, August 24, 1937; 4.
      - Mitchell's Secretary to Godfrey, September 3, 1937; 5.
      - Description of the English Room Architecture by Walter Godfrey, November 1937; 6.
      - Elevations of Godfrey's plan for the English Room, 1937; 7.
    - Correspondence, 1938-1946 (Item 3)
      - Summary of Discussions with Mrs. Mitchell and Dr. Bowman, March 31 and April 1, 1938; 1.
      - Extract of Letter from Mr. Godfrey, February 4, 1938; 2.
      - Department Request from Mitchell to Klimcheck, April 5, 1938; 3.
      - List of queries in connection with proposed English Room, Pittsburgh University, March 1938; 4.
    - Correspondence, 1939 (Item 4)
      - Godfrey to Mitchell, April 4, 1939; 1.
      - List of Drawings for English Room, April 28, 1939; 2.
      - Mitchell to Godfrey, April 28, 1939; 3.
      - Godfrey to Mitchell, August 9, 1939; 4.
    - Correspondence, 1946 (Item 5)
      - Godfrey to Mitchell, August 5, 1946; 1.
      - Godfrey to Mitchell, August 13, 1946; 2.
      - Architect's Fee and Terms of Payment, 3.
    - Printed Material (Item 6)
      - Third Annual Report of the National Buildings Record, April 12, 1944; 1.
      - Fourth Annual Report of the National Buildings Record, April 12, 1945; 2.
      - The Abbot's Parlour, Thame Park, 91929; 3.
  - Final Design for the English Room, 6.
    - Memorandum on Design, June 1949 (Item 1)
    - Revised Memorandum on Design, November 2, 1950 (Item 2)
    - Description of the Proposed Design for the English Room, A.A. Klimcheck, December 1950 (Item 3)
    - Memorandum on Conferences with Alfred Bossom, September 22, 1953 (Item 4)
    - Theodore Bowman to Mitchell, October 2, 1953 (Item 5)
    - English Room Financial Statement No. 1, December 12, 1952 (Item 6)
  - Correspondence relative to Improvemnet of the English Room, 1956-1958; 7.
    - Correspondence, 1956 (Item 1)
      - Memo from Elliott to Mitchell, April 6, 1956; 1.
      - Memo from Mitchell to Nutting, May 2, 1956; 2.
      - Memo from Mitchell to Nutting, May 4, 1956; 3.
      - Nutting to Fisher, May 15, 1956; 4.
      - Mitchell to Fisher, June 30, 1956; 5.
      - Fisher to Robert Samuel, July 3, 1956; 6.
      - English Room Committee Conference with Robert Samuel, August 3, 1956; 7.
      - Estimates for English Room Improvement, August 27, 1956; 8.
      - Mitchell to Fisher, November 28, 1956; 9.
      - Fisher to Ray Cross, December 7, 1956; 10.
      - Fisher to Robert Samuel, December 7, 1956; 11.
      - Bruce Allen to Fisher, January 10, 1957; 12.
    - Correspondence, 1957 (Item 2)
      - Robert Samuels to Fisher, January 16, 1957; 1.
      - Fisher to Mitchell, February 19, 1957; 2.
      - Bossom to Mitchell, March 27, 1957; 3.
      - Photo of Cabinet with dimensions, 4.
      - Memo from Mitchell to Elliott, July 23, 1957; 5.
      - Memo from Mitchell to Elliott, July 23, 1957; 6.
      - A.C. van Dusen to Elliott, October 30, 1957; 7.
      - Mitchell to A.C. van Dusen, November 12, 1957; 8.
      - Charles Elliott to Adolph Schmidt (draft), 9.
      - Handwritten notes, 10.
      - Richard Hadden to Elliott, November 25, 1957; 11.
      - Fleming to Elliott, December 1, 1957; 12.
      - J.D. Forbes to Walter A. Taylor, December 10, 1957; 13.
      - Turpin C. Bannister to Elliott, December 19, 1957; 14.
    - Correspondence, 1958 (Item 3)
      - Memo from Elliott to R. Hadden and Mitchell, January 6, 1958; 1.
      - Fisher to Samuels, February 18, 1958; 2.
      - Samuels to Fisher, March 6, 1958; 3.
  - Window Rondelles, 1952-1958; 8.
    - Correspondence, 1952 (Item 1)
      - English Room Committee recommndations, November 12, 1952; 1.
      - List of English Cities, 2.
      - List of Important Men with Coats of Arms, 3.
      - English Room Committee Addresses, November 8, 1952; 4.
      - Members of the General Committee, 5.
      - Brief History of Some English Colleges, 6.
      - Firth to Ruth Crawford Mitchell, November 26, 1952; 7.
    - Correspondence, 1953 (Item 2)
      - Weaver to Klimcheck, February 18, 1953; 1.
      - Klimcheck to Mitchell, February 20, 1953; 2.
      - William Pitt Coat of Arms, 3.
    - Correspondence, 1954 (Item 3)
      This section does not contain any pieces of correspondence. Instead, it cross references several letters between Ruth Crawford Mitchell and Alfred Bossom.
    - Correspondence, 1955 (Item 4)
      - Bossom to Mitchell, March 17, 1955; 1.
      - Firth to Rupp, April11, 1955; 2.
      - Dotter to Bossom, July 27, 1955; 3.
      - Master of Sinclair to Mitchell, August 4, 1955; 4.
      - Dotter to Master of Sinclair, September 4, 1955; 5.
      - Fyfe to Mitchell, September 21, 1955; 6.
      - Weaver to Klimcheck, October 14, 1955; 7.
      - Heaton-Armstrong to Mitchell, November 16, 1955; 8.
      - Fisher to Mitchell, November 9, 1955; 9.
      - Mitchell to Heaton-Armstrong, November 8, 1955; 10.
      - Mitchell to Fyfe, October 19, 1955; 11.
      - Mitchell to Firth, December 1, 1955; 12.
    - Correspondence, 1956 (Item 5)
      - Master of Sinclair to Mitchell, January 4, 1956; 1.
      - Mitchell to Master of Sinclair, November 8, 1956; 2.
      - Moore to Mitchell, December 20, 1956; 3.
    - Correspondence, 1957 (Item 6)
      - Elliott to Moore, January 16, 1957; 1.
      - Mitchell to Master of Sinclair, January 31, 1957; 2.
      - Master of Sinclair to Mitchell, February 5, 1957; 3.
      - Master of Sinclair to Mitchell, February 16, 1957; 4.
      - Mitchell to Klimcheck, April 3, 1957; 5.
      - Mitchell to White, July 16, 1957; 6.
      - Memo from Mitchell to Elliott, July 17, 1957; 7.
      - Memo from Mitchell to Elliott, October 31, 1957; 8.
      - Pittsburgh Stained Glass to the University of Pittsburgh, November 4, 1957; 9.
      - Hunt to Theodore Bowman, November 20, 1957; 10.
      - Memo from Mitchell to Elliott, December 11, 1957; 11.
    - Correspondence, 1958 (Item 7)
      - The Lord Sinclair to Elliott, January 22, 1958; 1.
      - Elliott to Master of Sinclair, January 15, 1958; 2.
      - Memo from Mitchell to Elliott, January 9, 1958; 3.
      - Memo from Elliott to Fisher, April 2, 1958; 4.
      - Hadden to Rupp, April 10, 1958; 5.
      - Memo from Elliott to Theodore Bowman, April 18, 1958; 6.
      - The Lord Sinclair to Elliott, April 29, 1958; 7.
      - Elliott to The Lord Sinclair, May 1, 1958; 8.
      - Moore to Elliott, May 7, 1958; 9.
      - Receipt for the paintings of Walls End and Ripon arms, 10.
      - The Lord Sinclair to Elliott, June 12, 1958; 11.
      - Mitchell to the Lord Sinclair, July 2, 1958; 12.
      - Mitchell to the Lord Sinclair, July 9, 1958; 13.
      - The Lord Sinclair to Mitchell, July 14, 1958; 14.
      - Firth letter to Donors, August 18, 1958; 15.
      - List of Medallions with Names of Donors, 16.
      - Financial Statement of the English Room Window Fund, 17.
  - Furniture, 1953-1959; 9.
    - Correspondence, 1953 (Item 1)
      - Mitchell to Fitzgerald, May 14, 1953; 1.
      - Fitzgerald to Mitchell, May 15, 1953; 2.
    - Correspondence, 1954 (Item 2)
      - Outline of Proposed Furnishings for the English Room, Januray 19, 1954; 1.
      - Estimate for Furniture, February 24, 1954; 2.
      - Cooley to Mitchell, July 22, 1954; 3.
      - Memo from Mitchell to Fisher, September 22, 1954; 4.
      - Memo from Mitchell to Fitzgerald, October 7, 1954; 5.
      - Memorandum Concerning Furniture of the English Room, October 14, 1954; 6.
      - Fisher to Mitchell, October 20, 1954; 7.
      - Memo from Fisher to Mitchell, October 29, 1954; 8.
      - Memo of meeting, October 29, 1954; 9.
      - Memo from Mitchell to Fisher, November 3, 1954; 10.
      - Mitchell to Firth, Martin, DeMoss, and Amundson, November 11, 1954; 11.
      - Firth to Fisher, November 22, 1954; 12.
    - Correspondence, 1955 (Item 3)
      - Memo from Mitchell to Fitzgerald, January 26, 1955; 1.
      - Memo from Mitchell to Fitzgerald, March 3, 1955; 2.
      - Mitchell to Fitzgerald, March 31, 1955; 3.
      - Mitchell to Mr. and Mrs. Firth, April 27, 1955; 4.
      - Memo from Mitchell to McFeaters, June 3, 1955; 5.
      - Fisher to Fitzgerald, June 10, 1955; 6.
      - Receipt from George Ciukurescu, September 20, 1955; 7.
      - Memo of Conference, October 13, 1955; 8.
      - Fisher to Mitchell, December 30, 1955; 9.
    - Correspondence, 1956 (Item 4)
      - Memo from Mitchell to Fisher, February 11, 1956; 1.
      - Coates to Klimcheck, February 16, 1956; 2.
    - Correspondence, 1957 (Item 5)
      - Photo of Display Case, 1.
      - Photo of Display Case with Dimensions, 2.
    - Correspondence, 1959 (Item 6)
      - Odey to Bossom, May 21, 1959; 1.
      - Drawing of fire side chair, 2.
- Volume V: Photographs: Classroom, Dedication, Special Events, Gifts, V.
  The final volume in this collection contains photographs of the English Nationality Room in various stages of construction, as well as its completion. Close up photographs of some of the features, including portraits, the fireplace, and windows, are also present. In addition, there are images of Alfred Bossom and some of the special events that have been hosted in the room, including the dedication of the English Room.
  - The English Classroom, 1.
    - English Room, showing fireplace (Volume 5, Item 1)
    - Mr. Aflred Bossom hanging the House of Commons stained glass medallion during the Dedication Ceremony, His Constituency is Maidstone in Kent, November 21, 1952 (Item 2)
    - Certificate of Appreciation, 1952 (Item 3)
    - Enid A. Hetterley, Lord Mayor of Sheffield 1981-82, on the occasion of her visit to the Nationality Rooms, November 17, 1981 (Item 4)
    - Mrs. R. C. Mitchell, Mrs. S.T. Patterson, Mrs. J. Scott, Mrs. C.W. DeMoss, Lady Wakehurst,Mrs. K.W. Todd, Mrs. J.W. Lawrence Pittsburgh Branch of English Speaking Union Luncheon for lady Wakehurst, wife of retiring Governor General of Australia and president Elect of English Speaking Union, London. (Item 5)
    - Old beams from 18th Century barn in Northern Pennsylvania through English Room window - used eventually for ceiling timbers and English Room tables (Item 6)
    - Sir Christopher Steel and Mr. Alfred C. Bossom with House of Commons stained glass Medallion at the Dedication Ceremony, November 21, 1952 (Item 7)
    - Mrs. Peter Gray member of the English room Committee and Mrs. Ruth C. Mitchell Director, examining pieces of paneling from bombed House of Commons (Item 8)
    - Photograph of old House of Commons from which paneling came (Item 9)
    - Photograph of etching of Dennis Flanders of the new House of Commons, 1950 (Item 10)
    - Sketch of English Room before completion made by Mr. Theodore Bowman (Item 11)
    - Sketch prepared by Mr. Theodore Bowman for carving of British Coat of Arms over the Entrance to the English Room (Item 12)
    - Old beam taken in through window of the English room for construction purposes (Item 13)
  - Dedication, November 21, 1952; 2.
    - English Room, showing fireplace (Item 1)
    - Photograph of Mr. Alfred Charles Bossom, M.P. Chairman of English Room Committee in London sent for use in Dedication Program, November 21, 1952 (Item 2)
    - Mr. Alfred Bossom, British Member of Parliament and Chancellor Rufus H. Fitzgerld, in English room (Item 3)
    - Mr. L. Gerald Firth, Chairman, English Room Committee hangs the stained glass medallion with the Insignia of his Alma Mater, Cambridge University, in the Oriole window during the Dedication Ceremonies, November 21, 1952 (Item 4)
    - Mr. William V. Griffin, National President of the English Speaking Union of the United States speaks after placing the bronze marker underneath the brick from 10 Downing Street, in the wall of the English Room at the Dedication Ceremony, November 21,1952 (Item 5)
    - Right to Left: Mr. William V. Griffin, National President, E.S.U. of U.S., Mr. Alfred C. Bossom, Member of Parliament, Sir Christopher Steel, Her Majesty's Minister to Wa. D.C., and Aide to Sir Steel in English Room, November 21, 1952 (Item 6)
    - The Rt. Rev. Austin Pardue, Bishop of Pittsburgh who gave the Invocation at the Dedication Ceremony, November 21, 1952 (Item 7)
    - English Room, looking towards entrance door (Item 8)
    - English room, showing Oriole windows (Item 9)
    - English Room as arranged at time of Dedication looking toward Oriole window (Item 10)
    - English Room under construction. Installation of stone bosses (Item 11)
    - Oriole window, English Room (Item 12)
    - Original Fireback, specially cast in 1588 to celebrate the defeat of the Spanish Armada (Item 13)
    - Carving in the English oak panel over the fireplace from the House of Commons selected by Mrs. Agnes L. Starret for overmantel panel and Lettering by Mr. Theodore Bowman (Item 14)
    - Water color print of English Room (Item 15)
    - Overmantel from Aye Lobby from bombed House of Commons after being putin position in English Room (Item 16)
    - Linenfold panels from the bombed House of Commons, set in frame work at end of English room. Fireplace shown with tile facing (Item 17)
  - Special Events, 3.
    - Dr. Albert Mansbridge: First Chairman of English Room Committee in London (Photograph of Portrait painted by son of Dr. Mansbridge) (Item 1)
  - Gifts, 4.
    - British Education Officer, J. Roger Carter, Wa. D.C. photographed with Chancellor Fitzgerald beside bust of the younger Pitt by English Sculptor J. Nollekins, R.A. taken on the occasion of the presentation by Mr. Carter of the gift of nest of walnut tables from Her Royal Highness Queen Mary, October 25, 1951 (Item 1)
    - Brick from No. 10 Downing Street, obtained by Mrs. Ruth Crawford Mitchell marked by a bronze ribbon by the English Speaking Union of the United States, at the Dedication Ceremony, November 21, 1952 (Item 2)
    - Showing fireplace and linenfold panels on either side of the English Room (Item 3)
    - Close up photo of one of the four stone bosses from bombed House of Commons used in supporting beamed ceiling in English Room (Item 4)
    - Carved and Polychromed British Royal Coat of Arms made in 1688, at the time of James II, the gift of a friend of Mr. Bossom (Item 5)
    - Alfred Bossom, Chairman, English Room Committee in London, showing Chancellor Fitzgerald the stained glass medallion he had made for the Oriole windows in the English Room - one of his many generous gifts (Item 6)
    - Photograph of portrait of William Pitt, First Earl of Chatham by William Hoare; Presented to the University of Pittsburgh by Carnegie Institute (the Painting is a copy of the original) (Item 7)
    - Photograph of Portrait of Andrew W. Mellon by Frank O. Salisbury; Gift of Ailsa Mellon Bruce (Item 8)
    - Original Andirons-1595, made in Sussex, England, from Sir Alfred C. Bossom, M.P. (Item 9)
    - Dr. Rosalind Branning, Associate Professor of Political Science, University of Pittsburgh, examining a brick from 10 Downing Street sent to the University by Mrs. R.C. Mitchell from London to be used in English Room, Summer 1936 (Item 10)
    - Flowers from Garden of Mr. L. Firth, Chairman of English Room Committee, being arranged for meeting of English Speaking Union. Left to Right: Mrs. Dodds, Mr. Firth, Mrs. Martin, Mrs. Firth (Item 11)
    - Hood of L.L.D. degree being conferred upon Alfred C. Bossom, M.P. at Dedication Ceremony, November 21, 1952 (Item 12)
    - Dr. Peter Gray, Professor of Biology, presenting gift of Sir Isaac Newton's Volume Philosophiae Naturalis Principia Mathematics at the Dedication Ceremony, November 21, 1952 (Item 13)
    - Academic Procession lead by University Marshalls Dr. Paul Masoner and Prof. P.W. Hutson, Dedication Ceremony, November 21, 1952 (Item 14)
    - Dr. Carroll J. Anderson, Professor of History, presenting the gift of the framed Magna Carta at the Dedication Ceremony, November 21, 1952 (Item 15)
    - Election of Queen Mother as Chancellor of University of London, sent by a friend and visitor to the English Room, Percy Dunseath, Chairman of Convocation, University of London, March 3, 1955 (Item 16)
    - British Education Officer, J. Roger Carter, Wa. D.C. shaking hands with Chancellor Fitzgerald on the occasion of presenting a gift of tables from Her Majesty the Queen Mother, October 25, 1951 (Item 17)
    - Mr. Roger W. Russell, Professor of Psychology at University of Pittsburgh, Visiting Professor, University College, University of London, and Mr. Alrfred C. Bossom, 1951 (Item 18)
    - Flowers placed in English Room as a tribute to the memory of Her Gracious Majesty Queen Mary, March 24, 1953 (Item 19)